so
in terms of generosity
in terms of generosity it's said that
even when if a monk is teaching people
the dhamma
you should start with teaching them
about generosity the benefits of giving
why well because generosity basically
forces you to give things up
like people's lives certainly people
that have not encountered dharma or or have
have not encountered dharma or or have
even a a vague
inkling towards you know relinquishment
dispassion letting go of attachments
it's all about gathering owning
increasing possessing
so the benefits of generosity it's
through generosity like generosity is
good and nice and it will make you feel
good it will make others feel good
even if you're still not interested in
dharma but also incidentally
generosity will make you give things up
and feel good on account of it
give something of yours part of your
wealth earnings
possessions and you will enjoy the fact
that somebody's happy on account of it
and can benefit from it and it's
grateful but you have actually given it up as
but you have actually given it up as
well and then so you enjoy as well
something that you gave up because yeah
it is
it is like it's a it's a factually
uplifting um less constricted state of mind
um less constricted state of mind
giving now you know there can be many
layers of giving
some people give by expecting stuff it
doesn't matter
in itself the phenomenon of giving does
require giving up i can't give it to you
if i don't give it up
as simple as that so that thread remains
wholesome throughout the giving even if
i give it you know
with a small print or something it's
still good to give
sure the best way to give is when you
yourself are completely not attached to
what you give it
so arahant giving to an arahant is the
greatest gift but mind you none of them
needs any merit anyway because there
aren't
so that's why the gift is purified by
the virtue of the giver or the virtue of
the receiver
as in how little he attached to these
things is
but as you're saying people get really
into it because
like it provides us i would say it
provides a sense of security
you know it does it does and it is it is
an uplifting need so it's not a it's not
just it's not just so it's all in your
head it's effectually uh a greater state of
it's effectually uh a greater state of
mind
than the mind of the one who doesn't
give because just look at it like if the mind
because just look at it like if the mind
the mind it doesn't give means the
it's the mind that always revolves
around habits of taking possessing
owning protecting worrying about it
having controlling
things that are unownable cannot be
protected and it will be taken away so the only
and it will be taken away so the only
way to sustain your state is to keep
doubling down in that sense that's why
it would have referred to
like a people with a miserly mind that
through lack of wisdom become like that
and they're then you know headed to bad
destinations and so on
not because they harmed anybody just
because they they constricted their mind
more and more and more
well giving prevents you giving it's
like a valve to that constriction
it will release that even if you don't
like it
even if you don't feel great on account
of giving the fact that you made
yourself give up something to someone else's
give up something to someone else's
benefit
it's good in that sense it will force at
least that extent of your mind to open
up
you know it's not like are you by giving
you give a piece of yourself away or
something that's just poetry
that people like to talk about no just
phenomenologically speaking
act of giving requires you to give up
at least that thing you give up more
means greater elevation of your mind
because you forced your mind to
back off step away from this you cannot
constrict yourself over this
so by giving you prevent mind to you
know with its own ignorance to kind of
develop the sense of ownership and latch
on it
and sure if you become attached to
giving great it's embedded
so you become attached to an elevated
state of mind it's still an attachment
but it's a better attachment on account
of the
attachment of generosity you actually
can get to even understand then
the purpose the true purpose of
generosity which is that
forcing your mind to expand
that's what generosity friendliness all
that goes hand in hand
it's a less limiting state of mind and
that's
not being generous being stingy
what why do you think a person does that
why would
why would a person be stingy insecurity
you know fear of proliferate non-control
sense of self
that it's now being threatened by even
mere things that sort of
you know you don't have or you can't
have
like the whole sense of self and the
ownership it's not this
fixed thing the more you the more you go
down that way
the more it will need for its
maintenance that so you have people who have
that so you have people who have
everything and still still
it's like never enough because they
psychologically became locked
into that pattern of always seeing that
it's never enough because
it cannot be on to begin with you can
have all the money but
fundamentally you feel that it's not
fundamentally in your control
deep down you know that why because you
could die at any given moment
the economy can crash at any given
moment thieves can come and steal it at
any given moment
and all that's implicit in your
ownership if you don't own it
how can you be affected if it changes or
goes away that's exactly the whole point
i mean when the buddha encouraged those
monks in the forest we said monks would
you be upset if people come and start
collecting these branches and
breaking them and burning them he says
no no we wouldn't
why is that because these branches
mean nothing they're not mined no
concern over them
exactly so that's how you should regard
your own body your own senses
things that you do have concern over
well remove the concern
recognize that in its nature it's truly
subjected to change and it's something
you cannot
affect or control or repossess
so people who are stingy or miserly lack
wisdom in that regard they see that that
is unchangeable
and they ignore it and as a result of it
they keep doubling down on the action of
more ownership and more control
because they ignore the fact that they
already know that it's not in their
control so there is this one suitor where
so there is this one suitor where
the buddha is speaking to a general
general see her
and that general asked the buddha what
are the benefits
visible here and now of generosity
and the buddha implies that there are
i think four benefits that you can see
here now
the fifth benefit is rebirthing or
the next yeah in future life you'll see
the benefit of birth in
heavenly realms right but you can't see
that now
so that's so that so the general just
goes by faith and he believes his buddha
sure so that's your face but the four
so that's your face but the four
benefits here now
is that people like you
because you give
a good that your a good reputation gets
spread and uh people uh wise people praise you
and uh people uh wise people praise you
and you are confident in amongst
any assembly of people whether it be
you know holy people royals
rich people skillful people yeah so why
would you be confident
like why why would you not be as
confident if you're not general
if you're not generous in any assembly
and then why would generosity make you
more confident
in any assembly because you know
you understand the quality well exactly
because as i said
it it's a it's a less limiting state of
mind you know lack of confidence is extremely
you know lack of confidence is extremely
constricted state of mind where you just
fear and insecure in regard to
everything and every movement and
others and so on so through generosity
as i said you're forcing your mind to
expand
it is a state of mind that is more
expansive than non-generosity
as simple as that and when the state of
mind is more expensive
it is less constricted less afraid
less being able to like you know twitch
to the left or to the right on the basis
of you know
perception of insecurities and so on
because it's more expensive
so it can take more and do you do more
of that
the more confident you will be not
conceited confident or something trying
to override everybody
no simply less moved because the mind is
broader
because what i saw in the suit is the
cure for
social anxiety that lots of people well
exactly yeah
social anxiety or anxiety because of
others because of which i don't engage with
because of which i don't engage with
others because of which my anxiety
increases because of which i don't engage with
because of which i don't engage with
others so it's a vicious circle
well generosity is a nice way to engage
with others
so you start breaking the vicious circle
of non-engaging with others
through engaging with others through
generosity and that little bit is enough to sort of
and that little bit is enough to sort of
set your mind at least
to some extent in that direction of wait
expansion like it's not intentional thing but by
like it's not intentional thing but by
being generous
you force your mind to like look look up
a bit
more and and they will diminish your
anxiety on a kind of
look down and hide it as simple as that
because there's
like that fear of not being liked or
being laughed at
being mocked exactly yeah and that will
remain something
not like you would not have those
thoughts if you if you if you've been
having those thoughts
but through generosity you get to
override them but
you get to elevate your mind above those
thoughts and then it doesn't matter if
they laugh at me or something
what matters is that i actually did the
generous deed
that's why generosity is a practice it's
not like you
you do a generous act and suddenly have
this religious experience although if
somebody's been very mildly you might
feel like that
any little expansion from extremely
constricted mind
will feel like a religious revelation
but generosity is a practice so you do it
generosity is a practice so you do it
you develop it you use wisdom obviously
you don't just start giving everything
carelessly you know when your own family is
you know when your own family is
starving or something but when you can
if you earn more
you always dedicate part for giving and
you don't overthink it
you don't make demands just find where
it's going to give to who can help who
can be helped
and do it and then practice doing it and
again you will build it up the behavior
of generosity
there will then be a phenomenon in your
mind seen as such
not just when you're giving even
generally i am a generous person and that
i am a generous person and that
knowledge will be there
and that's exactly the benefit of it
others that knowledge will be in others as well
that knowledge will be in others as well
not like you have to have audience when
you're giving all the time
but if you've been practicing giving
sufficiently enough
it would be known and you wouldn't care
whether it's known or not but it will be
known that's a fact that's what buddha
listed as one of the inevitable benefits
of it
so it's a practice that that should be
developed and uh and encouraged for individual
and uh and encouraged for individual
benefit
of your own mind expansion
and and benefit of others of course and
then it can
encourage others to be generous and help
which would then in return help their
own minds
from the state of you know stinginess uh
overly controlling possessive and so on
because again a simple reflection like
what what can you keep
what can you keep at the end of the life
but it's all this the idea but when you
die your possession will stay
yours but that idea exists in people's
minds just because they never think
about it but
being generous he says no no honestly
like how much do i need
and then you can always find a room for
some generosity and then make a practice
out of it